One example for uh is uh the famous
story of Notorious who was declared a
heretic at one of the early councils of
the churches because he couldn't make
it. He couldn't get there in time. His
church couldn't send representatives.
They're dealing in three different
languages. He said something or wrote
something in one document that was a bit
ambiguous about the nature of Christ.
But all of his other writing is so uh
classical, so orthodox and shows that
what he said here might have been, you
know, a twist of words or something like
that. Well, the council having only one
sentence said heretic gone, done. Having
now resourced to all of this stuff, the
churches as it were uh reintegrated in
the story into the Orthodox community,
the warm relations between the churches
that were that considered themselves in
story churches and all that. Well,
that's a research that you can do
quickly go through all of his literature
arrive at something. We had another girl
here from uh Syria. She was studying
manuscripts and she discovered that one
manuscript that had been attributed to a
certain author was not could not have
been uh uh his it had to be someone
else. And she could tell by the quality
of the language and then even date
things within the text. Well well again
it was the digitized process that
allowed her to see that quickly rather
than having to read through 400 books
and and go to Paris and go to different
countries and compare the uh the
volumes.
[Music]
Father David, Matthew, it's a real
pleasure to be with you this morning.
Um, we're here in Rome uh for uh as we
get ready to launch the uh Alexandria
digitization hub, which is a huge
project that you guys have been working
on for a very long time. Um, Father
David, if I may begin with you, can you
share the genesis of that project and
your collaboration with Matthew?
>> Sure. It's a series of births in in a
certain sense. It didn't start out as
one idea and then we were moving the
train out of the station to arrive at
another location. For us, the the
library of the Oriental, the Pontipical
Oriental Institute is unique in the
world. There's no library anywhere that
covers all of the Eastern churches. So,
the Eastern churches which come out of
Constantinople, the first church in
Jerusalem is an eastern church and so
on. So our library covers all of the the
churches. And when you say covers all of
the churches, it means it covers
languages, it covers history, covers
politics. Very often the first thing
that was written down was the Bible in
another language. Uh or translated. When
missionaries went from one country to
another, they had to translate the
Bible. They had to structure even the
alphabet in different languages. So the
the Bible's become great sources of
language, language development and
structure and all. So we have quite a
number of uh academics, researchers that
come to the oriental to use the library,
the resources of the library. Uh we have
students, it's basically a graduate
school. But the concern was not many can
come to Rome for a week or or a month
and use the resources. Isn't there a way
to make these uh resources more
available? And we're talking about a
geographical area from Russia to
Ethiopia, from southern Italy to
southern uh India. That's where the
eastern churches are. But even western
churches, bishops, scholars are
interested in these resources. So my
first interest was to digitize the
books. Get the books online for our
students, our past students, for
researchers, for scholars. We could even
have a a combined thing online of
several scholars studying a manuscript.
That would be an excellent thing. We
have perhaps 500 manuscripts in the
library. So that's how it began. And we
found some friends and benefactors, much
of it through Matthew's uh help and
inspiration. People came here, sent a
big scanners. Uh people came from New
York, experts in digitizing and began
the process of digitizing our own
publications.
And it was kind of magical like in in a
certain sense it was simple what they
were doing. Highdensity photographs of
everything they were digitizing 600 dpi
we could reduce to PDFs and make them
available. But immediately there was the
question, it would be nice if these
could be researched by word and uh and
not just pull pulling down a book or
pulling down an article. So as we went
on digitizing, we bought a scanner, we
got another scanner and we had two
people hired to scan more and more
books. And then uh we were looking
initially at one set of software that
was being developed that would allow
researchers to do research on a
manuscript. But it was really with the
arrival of AI that transformed our
possibilities. So, first getting the uh
text off of a PDF onto a computer
language that could be easily researched
by word without errors. But then our
library has I don't know if it has uh 20
or 30 languages in it, ancient
languages, modern languages. And so if
you want to research something, you want
to cross the languages. So we might have
the works of John Chrysum in four
different languages. And even that has a
value for scholars. How did they
translate this word into another
language? Again, when you look at
history, the the arguments over the
interpretations of who the nature of
Jesus, of the creeds, a word like uh
person in English in Italian sounds
pretty straightforward. But the word
persona in Greek means it can mean the
mask that you wear in a play. So is that
the best translation to make? So you see
the debates of scholars uh from,00500
years ago trying to deal with these
changes. Well again to be able to put
these things online you use AI
technology so that you're vectorized.
You're looking for concepts rather than
words in one language. So you take the
word nature or person and conceptually
you translate that into all of the
languages that are available to the AI
program and you search through the
entire library. So the richness for
research and for analysis is really
quite extraordinary.
>> Wow. That's that's so inspiring. And
then Matthew um when when father David
came in with these um with these you
know this goal of digitizing the the
patrimony of the church and and making
the the content and the books available
from uh the oriental to the students
around the world. What were some of the
technical challenges that that you
faced?
Well, I mean think when we started the
project, we weren't thinking so, you
know, big as like the patron of the
church. I mean, that's something that
that we now uh are focused more on, but
yeah, initially it was just let's just
trying to make sure that these resources
the eastern church are made more
available. And then, you know, there was
always the idea that if it worked and we
could expand it. Um there were a bunch
of technical challenges. I mean, you
know, one is the books themselves and
you know, uh father David can um speak
more to this than I can, but you know,
many of these books were very different
from each other, right? Some had very
delicate bindings, you know, some of
them more modern books, not so much.
Some of them are very large books, some
of them are very small. And and so, you
know, as much as possible, you want the
robot to do mo most most of the work
here, right, with the with the arm,
which, you know, the robot arm turns the
pages and does the scanning for you. So,
we're trying to automate the process as
much as possible, kind of reduce the
human in the loop, and just to allow us
to increase the rate at which we're
scanning. But, uh, but obviously, you
know, every time you you change the book
out, you have to kind of redial in um,
you know, the robot so it understands
what kind of text it's working with. so
it can effectively turn the pages. So
that I know that was that was a
challenge and I I know that that the two
uh lovely women who who work in there
have become something of of experts at
kind of sizing up books and and learning
how to dial in the robots. So there's
still very much like a collaboration
between you know the robots and human
beings at this stage. But you know the
hope is that we'll be able to figure out
new ways and and deliver kind of new
technologies into the hub which will
allow for further and further
automation. So we less less dependent
upon people uh you know in this process
and that will allow us to scan more. So
I would say that would that would be one
technical challenge that continues to
this day. I I will just say that we're
starting to look at some interesting
approaches. I'm sure some people may
have seen some articles about how laser
technologies and you know kind of like
CT scanning are being used to kind of
see through books and especially like
manuscripts which are very delicate,
right? Which they're afraid to kind of
open up for the purposes of scanning.
And so there's there's new technologies
on the scene I think that show a lot of
promise which would allow us to to scan
the books without actually having to
necessarily open them up and turn the
pages which in some cases could damage
them. So I think the future is very
bright for for digitization. I I said
that the second kind of biggest
challenge was and fellow David kind of
spoke to it is how do we extract the
information from the pages and then and
make sure that because you know OCR
optical character recognition um which
is something anyone uses Adobe PDF is
familiar with because it allows it's
what allows you to to take an image and
and then allow it to select the text
right that's because Adobe programs you
know run this optical character
recognition on it but it's a bit flaky
right so if you were to go and like copy
all the text from a my a PDF document
typically and paste it into a text, it's
a bit of a mess, right? There can be all
kinds of weird characters in there.
There's no formatting. And and and I'm
talking about like kind of, you know,
these are kind of like more simpler
problems. For more complex text, there
can be all kinds of artifacts and
things. And so so one of the human in
the loop challenges was that somebody
had to go um if you're trying to extract
information from the PDFs and clean it
up. You had to kind of clean up all the
noise. And in many cases, you had kind
of had to label the text, you know,
what's a header, like what's what's a
footnote, you kind of had to put that
information in. And you had to do all
this labeling before you kind of would
go through this process of then like
digitizing it. Um and and and I say
digitizing kind of a classical sense,
not not in the the AI sense. And so what
we were um trying to figure out is is
there a way that we could we could run
this extraction and it basically bring a
AI into the game so it could actually
handle all the the cleanup all all the
labeling of you know the text and then
also handle automatically this this
process of converting it from first to
kind of vector embeddings which kind of
makes this text language agnostic for
people to to query and then finally to
to a format called TEI which is like an
archiving standard which is kind of a
rich metadata format. This is all to say
that this whole process of of figuring
this out was was was something that we
felt if if we could crack this and have
AI do this part of the job. This would
allow us to significantly speed up
digitization mainly because there's a
lot of scanned content around the world
scanned for archival purposes but there
never been extraction run on it which
means you couldn't really effectively
query it. So if we figured if we could
we focused here on on this on this this
particular problem this could allow us
to unlock all those PDFs which are just
kind of sitting around for for storage
purposes. and we and and to date we've
been able to pretty much automate that
process.
>> That's extraordinary. And um Father
David um of course the library is at the
center of of of the university and and
and the educational programs that your
students from around the world are
coming. How have how has this project um
impacted their studies like making these
texts available for for students who for
for whatever reason might not be able to
attend class or come to Rome physically.
how has how has this um digital you know
documentation interacted with them and
also um where do you see this going? How
do you see this impacting their studies
in the future?
>> Well, I think one of the things that
that we had to consider quickly was the
pedagogy
because obviously a concern would be
plagiarizing and which is always a
concern anyway but now you you can cover
your plagiarizing pretty quickly. So uh
one of the concerns of the the Vatican
which heads uh um all all universities
that have a Catholic name on them are
under the opaces general oposes of the
diccastastery for education at the
Vatican and it tries to oversee and
promote certain aspects of education and
one that likes to guarantee is
interpersonal stuff so that not
everything is online not everything is
at distance not everything is through
your computer screen because there is
something that a mother communicates
ates to a child that a book on mothering
doesn't communicate to a child. So uh
and questions and answers that kind of
interaction. Well, what this this
process did was it made it more
important to have more meetings between
professors and students. So a student
would present their doctoral project,
their doctoral proposal. And that's a
fairly articulate process. They have to
have a bibliography and a direction to
go. A board of professors sit with the
student. They work it out, approve it or
change it, whatever. Then the student
has to return after the first pre piece
of research and say if the student is
writing in Italian and you know the
quality of the person's Italian and now
the student is writing like Dante
knowing the student you know what's
happened. So if when you have regular
meetings instead of waiting till the
dissertation is finished you can
challenge the student with the content
that the student has written. Do you
understand what you've written? What are
the implications of this? And so you
have a more interpersonal focus in the
educational process and the student has
to defend even if they they've used
whatever AI tools the student has to
defend what he or she has has written.
So oddly the technology has improved
human communication which is the last
thing we always expect with the with the
uh with AI and digitization.
Another thing the benefit that it offers
is uh there have been mistakes uh made
academically uh in the past for clear
reasons
uh that can now be researched in a more
clear concise and quick way. One example
for is uh the famous story of Notorious
who was declared a heretic at one of the
early councils of the churches because
he couldn't make it. He couldn't get
there in time. his church couldn't send
representatives. They're dealing in
three different languages. He said
something or wrote something in one
document that was a bit ambiguous about
the nature of Christ. But all of his
other writing is so classical, so
orthodox and shows that what he said
here might have been, you know, a twist
of words or something like that. While
the council having only one sentence
said heretic gone, done. Having now
resourced to all of this stuff, the
churches as it were uh reintegrated in
the story into the Orthodox community,
the warm relations between the churches
that were that considered themselves in
story churches and all that. Well,
that's a research that you can do
quickly go through all of his literature
arrive at something. We had another girl
here from uh Syria. She was studying
manuscripts and she discovered that one
manuscript that had been attributed to a
certain author was not could not have
been uh uh his it had to be someone
else. And she could tell by the quality
of the language and then even date
things within the text. Well well again
it was the digitized process that
allowed her to see that quickly rather
than having to read through 400 books
and and go to Paris and go to different
countries and compare the uh the
volumes.
That's extraordinary. And then Matthew,
as as we get ready to to, you know,
start um to really maximize the hub as
as the scanners come in and as they
start to um really the work comes
underway, what what is that going to
look like? Can you break it down and
kind of walk us through those steps?
>> Sure. I mean, so we embarked on this
this kind of proof of concept, you know,
I think it was almost a couple years
now. So we had this kind of robot
scanner. We had this kind of high-end
manual scanner for more delicate
manuscripts. and we really just want to
kind of push the technology to see how
far we we could get with it. And so I
mean we think we still think there's a
long way for the hardware to go but um
certainly the robo scanner is is
helpful. So we said okay uh so it's
working um we we need to figure out this
whole digitization process and that's
kind of the last year what we've been
really working on is how far can we push
AI in this whole uh this this whole
automated uh ingestion process and and
uh I think I think we've we've close to
cracking there's still some work to do
obviously um you know father David
mentioned to it I mean one of the one of
the unique challenges in this ingestion
work is you know some of these books
have languages which are ancient right
and and so what this means effectively
for AI is the AI are not able to embed
them which is basically kind of convert
um to ma to map the text semantically
effectively right and and basically
convert it into into math that the AIS
can read and understand numbers and
that's namely because embedding models
are are trained on large corpuses of
data like large language models and uh
and and if they're their training data
the distribution of the train data
doesn't consist of large swaths of of
that of let's say a particular language
it's just not capable of effectively
embedding it so that's not to say that
the AI are useless at it that they may
still get it 50 or 60% correct because
they can look at you know the
relationship between other languages and
they can kind of make inferences but
there's still a long long way to go
there. So I I I think for most of the
conventional languages that are spoken
today and and some some of the ancient
languages like Latin and Greek um you
know the AI process is still working
very effectively. So, and and I think
that in of itself is going to be
enormously beneficial considering
specifically because the church's
historical language has been Latin,
there's a lot written in it. But I I
think there there is an opportunity here
um to to kind of tap into these experts
in these ancient languages and and help
them to kind of develop uh training data
sets so we can kind of trade into to
basically train a better embedding model
which is more capable of understanding
these languages and therefore mapping
them more effectively. Um so so that's
that's a research project that I'm
looking forward to embarking you know
with the Pontific University in Rome. Um
but so the immediate next step is let's
let's get more scanners. Let's just
speed this up, right? We there's there's
a lot of books here among some
Pontipical universities. I mean the
Gregorian and the Orientality and
Biblical libraries alone are absolutely
massive. So so we we knew we needed, you
know, two scanners would not be near
enough. So we bought another five five
scanners. So we'll have a bunch of
robots in there in working away. And I
still consider this a kind of a a a
proof of concept. And and the idea is
that we're going to have a webcam on the
deal so people can actually watch the
books being scanned and and and
hopefully we'll have an inventory so
people can kind of check where their
book is in the scanning queue and and
and see when it's going to be scanned.
And we think that'll be kind of fun. Um
but the idea is we want to show people
what this process consists of and and
get them excited about it. And I think
it's it's especially like exciting
because when a book is is on the scanner
that day, as soon as a scanning job is
done, it takes sometimes an hour or two
to process all the information and then
it's immediately available to to you
know any of the users within Vulgate or
if the book is if they that the
university has decided they want to open
source that information it can be made
made available to you know millions of
users through Magister AI. So this is
it's quite extraordinary to think that
you know a book that was just literally
scanned by a robot within a few hours is
then available to anyone in the world to
scan and drive insights from. So, and I
think once people realize um you know
ultimately what this will mean for
scholarship and I think just gen you
know generally uh just for for even uh
you know for us ordinary folk right who
are just looking for uh some insight
from the church to help us in our
day-to-day lives. I I think I think
it'll garner a lot of attention and then
what we're hoping is we can do is we can
then raise potentially some funds
philanthropically you know maybe from
from the grassroots from from some some
donors and foundations to expand the the
scanner fleet and and and hopefully
invest in development of of even better
hardware. Um the final phase that I'm
I'm looking forward to and I I I say
final in quotation marks because I I
don't really know where this project
will ultimately go but um obviously
having the hub in Rome is exciting.
There's a lot of lot of libraries, a lot
of content here and we could we'll be
scanning for years but there's obviously
there's there's great repositories of
information um materials that should be
scanned documents books all all over the
place. So the question is how do we get
the scanners to them? And so one of the
things we're looking at now is is kind
of the development of a flying hub where
where we kind of build some scanners
which are a little bit easier to kind of
take apart and and reassemble and uh and
that way the scanners can can go to the
works and that will allow us to get our
hands on more and more.
>> It's extraordinary. And then Father
David, I mean we know that there's there
there's so many um resources there's so
many important books and documentation
here in Rome um working you know within
the the Pontipical University system.
This is something that, you know, from
my eyes seems like it's very much at the
forefront. It's an innovation. It's
something that I I don't know of any
other university doing this. Um, what is
what has it been like for you bringing
this mission, bringing this this, you
know, this really unique and new idea to
the Pontipical Universities and and to
the eternal city which does not have the
reputation for always being the the
quickest adapter.
>> Yeah. Well, it's it is true. When we
were conceiving some aspect of this
project, uh the first books that we were
digitizing and how can we access them, I
looked around the world, Europe and
North America, at big universities that
had resources and nobody had a program
that could do anything better than uh
OCR reading of a PDF file, which shocked
me. I mean, we're not heavily funded. we
don't have $15 billion in reserve that
as as a lot of universities uh bigger
universities would have. So but at the
same time uh I was concerned that the
church should be on the cutting edge of
this stuff. So uh so again it just it's
providential. It's serendipitous.
Matthew and I uh knew each other here.
We had other people who were interested
people offering their scanners for this
trial experiment sort of thing. So even
though the the um AI technology is
changing rapidly, digitizing technology
is changing. It could be more rapid, but
it's it's changing. It's important for
the church to be on the forefront of
this kind of thing. Even to give
direction about where it should or
shouldn't go is one thing to be making
its resources available. I mean the
church is about the gospel which is the
word and communication and creating
community. So the more broadly that we
can do that, the better it is. I
wouldn't say it's a risk, but it's it's
a kind of a nervous excitement that the
technology is changing so quickly. We
would not have imagined where we are
today, say two years ago,
>> and the rapid changes in AI. The first
AI program was magical. Wow, it can do
this. The second iteration was, wow, now
it can do this. And then the third
iteration. So, so we're chasing
something, but we're chasing something
that makes sense, that already has a
fruit, you know. So, um, and who knows
where it'll go. Matthew was mentioning
that languages. We study here some, uh,
let's call them weird languages, uh,
dead languages, Nimidian, Scabodian,
that you could all of the people that
can read these languages, you could put
into one small classroom, you know, and
yet important documents are written in
uh, in these languages. Now they have
languages today that that share the same
root. But how do you understand that
language in its context only through
other literature uh that was written
which is again the importance of having
not just scripture in that language but
all the other books of politics of
whatever geography science from that
language understand the uh the
connotations that are in the word at the
time and the latest uh programs Google
is very big in this but not only Google
is analyzing a language that nobody
really knows with the benefit of
languages that have already been studied
uh ancient languages and giving
indications how to break down this
language and how to understand it. So
again even that sort of thing is very
informative for the kind of research
that we're doing here. So being at the
forefront, kind of being at the cutting
edge, introducing these new technologies
in a way that is having absolute good,
absolutely good results and not worrying
about are they going to clone babies,
are they going to scan dogs, you know,
or something like that, but but showing
that good examples, how the technology
can be used.
>> That's extraordinary. And then, Father,
speaking on on that potential for good,
um we know that of course um you know,
if you just turn on the news today,
there's obviously lots of conflict, lots
of tension. Um and of course in the
oriental you know kind of sphere there's
there's um there is tension and violence
and stuff uh with the AI being able to
help with with uh documentation
communication clearing up and and and
making you know evident aspects of
translations uh traditions and and just
uh making that scholarship available on
a global uh stage. It seems like the
potential for ecumenical dialogue,
interreligious dialogue, uh you know,
true scholarship across bound is it
seems like the potential is is immense
for that. Can you speak a little bit on
on that importance and how how this
technology, the scanners, the hub, um
magisterium, you know, are is going to
be able to contribute to that?
>> Yeah, it it's it's strong and it's weak
at the same time because a lot of it
depends on human beings. So if human
beings don't want to they won't if human
beings are presented with the truth they
don't want to hear they won't listen. So
that's there and but on the other hand
uh the other aspect is absolutely true
once it's there in reliable
documentation once it's there in
demonstrable fact once it's there
historically and and anybody can look at
it and research it is harder to get away
with a lie. You still can but it is
harder to get to get away with a lie.
and and people of goodwill on both sides
of an argument will find that and the
example I gave of the churches having
come together. Uh this happens you know
once once the ground is clear but the
you know the the problem is always human
beings you know and uh but but again the
the the opening up the truth opening up
the facts uh they become harder and
harder to resist when they're broadly
available and not just locked in in a
library. And father, can you can you
share a little bit on how your students
are interacting with um with these
digitized documents? How, you know,
maybe in the classroom or if they're
they're going abroad for for a visit or
for um you know, an exchange program.
How how is um how is this um digital,
you know, technology coming into the
classroom in a practical sense and
helping them, you know, on their
everyday studies? Yeah, I would say
we're still early in that and obviously
the the younger generation is much more
adept at the at the technology than the
professors who are in the classroom. So
the uh I would say right from the
beginning three professors were gung-ho
about it. the other 50 well you know and
then ironically covid came and then
there were major conversions among the
other professors when they saw what the
technology could do uh both the visual
technology in the classroom and then the
access to books so I would say as a it's
still in a in a kind of experimental
stage not in a sense that it's an
experiment that we'll reject but we're
learning as we go and for the professors
to learn how to integrate digitized
resources into study process processes
into uh textual research and all of that
and affirming or having cautions or
challenging students in this or that
direction. Uh and again more and more
students wanting to come here for have
to have access to the resources. But
we're still at a learning stage of how
better to make these things available.
For example, one thing that that we
couldn't do so easily before we would
have to have a conference and bring in a
bunch of professors from around the
world to study a manuscript. And now
they can do that online. They can make a
copy of a certain text. All of them can
annotate it in their various languages
and have this kind of visual discussion
over a text online. Go back and forth
with it. The document is saved with all
their annotations. Come back to it in a
week. So the the possibility that's
already there, but the the possibilities
for enhanced high-end academic research
and documents is really really quite
quite rich. Um and then Father David,
can you share a little bit about how
you've transformed the Pontipical
Oriental Institute, brought you know,
new technologies made um you know,
recording digital access to the
classrooms? If you could share that for
our audience.
>> Mhm. There are funny things with
technology. when I was uh in Canada and
I worked with native people on a reserve
in northern Ontario and all of a sudden
mobile telephones came out and I grew up
in Toronto and here with the irony was
that everyone in Toronto had a mobile
phone had a phone a stationary phone at
home and a network of phones in their
office and we were up in the bush and
have no way of communicating with one
another. you have to drive 2 hours to to
give a message to someone and it was
that's where the technology was needed
not uh in the city but so it's it's now
uh everywhere well there was something
similar here is that in um at
universities I would say generally but
maybe more specifically in Rome come to
us and you can enjoy our resources which
is easier said than done for like 99% of
the world so um so again the whole thing
of when I came here there was not much
technology in the building just in
principle. I wanted to have technology,
modern technology in all of the
classrooms. And again, I could find some
resources to get this done. Again, I
would say most of the professors here
said, "Well, well, if he can do it,
okay, we're not going to stand in the
way. Let let him go ahead and do this."
And again, two or three loved it, saw
the advantage of using it. And we were
using Google and Google for education
and and the professors who um could
understand the technology quickly. They
enhanced learning for the students right
away in the classroom. So we put in uh
uh
television screens. We don't have any
overhead projectors anymore, but it's
all large screens uh in the classrooms.
We brought in Google technology uh
microphones and speakers. And if it was
a big classroom, we might have six sets
throughout the classroom. Uh if it was a
smaller classroom, there might be two
sets of speakers and microphones. And
again, there was high quality stuff that
Google was was producing. And then you
you run into other things that some
classrooms had an echo in them. Again,
these buildings are of a certain age.
One part of the building that we're in
was built in the 15th century. So you
you have to think of how can we retain
the architecture and yet uh update the
whole stuff. So there there are people
around who know this kind of thing. We
had two classrooms which professors
refused in principle ever to use because
there was an echo and we had experts
come in and they said in these two
classrooms there's a reverberation of
more than 3 seconds. Now you think about
it the students come from around the
world. They're studying in Italian. For
a lot of those students it might be
their fifth language. Uh the professors
come from around the world. The language
that they're instructing in is Italian.
and it might be their third or fourth
language. So professor is speaking with
an accent, the students are listening
with an accent and there's an echo in in
the room. So uh so again we brought in
these experts and it's incredibly
inexpensive to do this and even
aesthetically you can do it well. So we
put in absor sound absorption panels
aesthetically on the walls and in the
ceiling and changed the lighting a bit.
And the one professor who said he would
never teach in that classroom said now
this is my favorite classroom. I spent
half of my life in classrooms. I never
said I had a favorite classroom. But now
that's the way even students were
reacted to that. So we studied color. We
studied light intensity. And so they say
500 lumens per square meter is ideal for
study and research. The colors that uh
aid uh re um conversation, life, energy
are yellows and oranges and and and
reds. So we repainted everything uh
without toxic chemicals in the colors.
And again you could see you could see
the difference. So uh even business
technology will talk about creating a
space of joy. So, I don't know how many
students get up and say, "Oh, boy, I'm
going to class today, but you do create
an environment that is enjoyable to be
in. The chairs are comfortable to sit
in. The colors keep you awake. You can
hear everything that's being said."
Another funny thing that we put into the
main conference room was, this is when
uh Matthew first came was we teched up
the the main conference room. So, with
all the standard technology and all, but
we put in five rotating cameras. And one
of the curious things with this, this
was just interesting to see on on the
big screen and of course were connecting
with the the world, those who wanted to
see the thing online, but the cameras
would then rotate around the uh the
conference hall. So students and
professors who are sitting and listening
would have the camera on them all of a
sudden. So what was one of the effects?
Less sleeping during conferences and all
that stuff. So there was a fun aspect,
there was an academic aspect, uh there
was an energy aspect to the study and
all. And then when as I say when co came
along Google again did as many companies
did a generous thing they allowed the
full extent of uh Google+ education plus
for all Google education users which
means that you can record the sessions
without having to pay extra. For our
students that was really quite rich uh
because they could listen to the the
lecture a second time in Italian and and
pick it up whatever they were missing.
And what we found was they came back to
the next lesson full of clear questions
and the professors themselves were
shocked that there all of a sudden the
students are intelligent but they had
the chance to listen to it a second
time. So again you're going to say this
is technology pretty basic pretty simple
but it transformed the quality in the
classroom and professors commented on
that the work the students are doing is
better the papers they're writing are
better the instruction is better.
They're coming back with better
questions. So again you you saw the
intelligent use of technology had great
human effect. It's about the human
being. It's about the human context. If
it serves that it can do a great job and
then it was just step by step from that
level of technology kind of a very human
quality of technology to the next step
that we're that we're talking about
here. So you just see this multiplier
effect. And again as I would say the
church is the group that the church is
created for good. it should be on the
cutting edge of using this stuff for
good, showing others the possibilities
that's that's in the technology.
>> That's that's so extraordinary. And um
and Matthew uh you know working in in
the tech sphere and and you know kind of
seeing also how quickly this is evolving
and and hearing from father David you
know that these you know these changes
are are radically transforming in such a
positive way the the learning
environment and the the educational
format for for students from around the
world. Where do you see this technology
going? I mean we see so you guys are
digitizing um books and bringing that
and vectorizing it and making that
knowledge base available to the world.
What what other plans do you have? Where
where do you see this going in the
coming years?
>> Well, I mean I I think ultimately I mean
Father David said it. I mean what we're
really trying to figure out is is what
is the kind of most optimal way one to
kind of disseminate this information and
make sure it's practically useful to as
many people as possible. I mean this is
this is kind of what really drives the
company. the quest to build and scale
Catholic AI which is our primary mission
and us we had a secondary mission to
digitize the patch of the church because
that serves the primary mission. Um this
is this is really just about making sure
that all of this great insight right
that you know very few of us got a
chance to go to seminary or or get you
know m study study theology and
philosophy right and and so we we know
the enormous benefit that that that
comes from from taking that time away to
study these these things and for a lot
of people never had that opportunity.
It's it's it's very unfortunate and in
some ways this has been kind of a very
clerical lay divide, right? And so what
I what I see is a real kind of exciting
opportunity here is is by making all
this information available distilling it
for people is that we can kind of close
that gap a little bit, right? So anybody
who's got, you know, questions, you
know, existential questions or wants to
probe church teaching more deeply. Well,
well, now they have a place they can go
and they can do that, right? And and the
AI can patiently work with them, right?
And they can move at their own pace.
This is something so we talk about like
the the future next steps. One thing I'm
really excited about is is the
opportunities for AI to actually be able
to kind of adapt its pedagogical
approach for each student right um to
help them learn more effectively. And I
think you know if you think of the old
traditional paradigm I think actually we
go way back to the University of Paris I
think when Thomas Quanis was teaching
it's very different but the modern
paradigm is you maybe have you know and
maybe a high school you got 50 50
students you got one one teacher they
have a curriculum they need to teach and
and they do their thing right they they
teach that curriculum and of course
those 50 students are are really pretty
unique they're all different places so
sometimes that that particular way of
teaching is is not overly effective
maybe for some but but not for everyone
and that's just unfortunately that's
just the best we've been able to do you
ideally I think everyone would would
prefer that there was a much smaller you
know uh teacher to to student ratio
right so they get more personalized
education but how do we do this it just
seems practically ineffective well well
now with something like AI we can do
onetoone right in principle um if you
have a curriculum and and you provide
the AI access to it and you use
something like voice mode because
student can actually talk to and
interact you know with the AI and the AI
can actually kind of teach and based on
on on how the students um receiving and
and being able to you know explain um
the concepts back to the AI can say is
this working Isn't it working? And if
it's not working, it can try let me try
adapting my pedagogical approach until
it finds one that works really well. So
like there are there are leaders like
Khan Academy like Sal Khan who've been
demonstrating how this technology uh can
be used to kind of really lift people
out of poverty. Khan Academy is an
incredible example. It's been very very
it started you know it's very very big
in India and and I think the Catholic
Church which has been a pioneer in
education right from since since since
its very beginning there's a real
opportunity for us to kind of establish
ourselves as a leader again um by by by
because because primarily because we
don't look at education as a business
right I this is something this is
something we're doing uh as is something
to advance the common good we care about
the human person and so we can afford to
kind of kind of move those business
those those business incentives aides
the economic incentives sides even the
political and ideological things aside
and say listen ultimately what we want
is is for every person to flourish. So
um what tools and technologies what
approaches can we use to most
effectively ensure that that that that
that's the outcome. And so because of
that openmindness and that kind of
mission first approach to education. I
think that there's a real opportunity
for the church to be an early adopter in
this technology and is and to
demonstrate its effectiveness. One one
of the great advantages of what we're
talking about in terms of the AI
technology is that uh it's we're talking
about a closed system of research. So
what do I mean by that? If you're the
the magisterium site or the Vulgate
site, you're not getting uh what is
Uncle Bob thinking about Jesus now? You
know, you're getting the classic texts,
the teaching of the church. And so it's
a reliable source of uh of research. And
the second thing is people uh would
worry about well if AI is teaching me am
I going to go astray? Well again this is
a bit the challenge at putting together
a thing. But on the other hand you say
do all of us believe everything that
every teacher has told us from the
beginning to the end that no teacher has
ever made a mistake. Well you know
welcome to life. You're going to hear
different sides and different opinions
but it's the human being that has to put
the the pieces together you know. So
there there's a challenge for the these
technologies that we're talking about to
make them as reliable uh intelligent as
as possible uh to serve uh human human
beings but not to be too preoccupied
about is there going to be a mistake
here or a mistake there if I decide to
do some weird thing because of something
I saw on YouTube there's something wrong
with me you there's not something wrong
with the technology you know
>> and father David how do you see
education changing as we, you know, as
we continue to progress into the AI era,
there's a lot of students, you know,
who, you know, in high school now, kids
in college, and they're, um, you know,
they're working on things. They're
they're trying to, you know, secure
their future, work to towards getting a
job, and of course, that landscape is
changing. How do you see um the role of
education, the role of universities
changing to to guide to to you know to
form students but also to prepare them
for what could be an uncertain and and
somewhat you know daunting future but
also one that has the potential you know
for for more time to study to form to
you know all the upside as well.
>> Yeah. I I don't know how well
universities uh can do that. There there
is a certain aspect where universities
are reactionary something is going on
now we'll study it and then maybe we can
work on a solution but to prepare in
advance for it we don't know I don't
think universities and and schools are
are best adapted to that again and we
don't know what the next 5 years of uh
this technology will bring certainly a
preoccupation is uh the job market
what's going to happen with so many jobs
with advances in AI and all this
And one of the classic principles of
Catholic education has always been the
development of the human being. So it's
the full development of the human being.
So it's it's being a breast of what's
going on. It's is my identity attached
to technology or is am I getting too
depressed about something that's going
on? The creativity of the human being
entering uh this world with creativity
with energy looking for new
possibilities. It isn't the first time
that we're going through kind of a
social upheaval. And so it's going to uh
ask for mature people to face this with
honesty to walk through the fears and
the preoccupations and the concerns to
maintain a level of justice. And the
classic example that the current pope uh
refers to is Leo the 13th. At the height
of industrialization, people were losing
jobs everywhere. There were no labor
laws. You could be forced to work 16
hours a day at 12 years of age and all
this. So it took a bit of time to catch
up with that to create the laws uh
systems uh ages age limits for for work
and retirement ages and all that that
took most of the 20th century to refine.
Pension laws came in in the midh 20th
century. Uh health care universal
healthcare came in after the second
world war in many countries. So this
stuff you're you're reacting to. So as
best we can prepare the human being for
facing uh the current day without fears
without um uh over concerns or
preoccupations of what or might not be
but to enter it with courage and
imagination I think that's the best that
we can hope for from education
>> and I think you know this might be an
opportunity for us to kind of get back
to first principles when it comes to
universities right I I think um too much
even Catholic universities have gone I
think of I've kind of given way to this
pressure, right? To
that you know the the purpose of a
university today is for you to achieve a
degree, right? To get a piece of paper
so that you can qualify for a job,
right? And then so and you need a job
because you need to get a mortgage,
right? And then you need to be able to
have money in order for to put your kids
through college, right? And so it's just
this kind of cycle. And um but that's
not what education is supposed to be
about, right? And and I think for if you
look at like I when I was going through
high school, I think probably a lot of
people kind of sh experience. I mean I I
didn't spend a lot of time um exploring
what my my true gifts are. I just didn't
have much of an imagination for it. I
mean there's some things I liked more
than others and stuff, but I I didn't
spend a lot of time and certainly I
didn't feel in the in the kind of the
classroom environment that we spend a
lot of time focusing on Matthew. Let's
let's figure out who you are and what
you're good at, right? And so that we
can kind of figure out how you can hone
those gifts and skills to serve. And
that makes sense, right? Especially when
you have one teacher for 50 students.
Yeah, there's only you have to be
reasonable in your expectations. So, you
know, I kind of feel like that
universities can get back to what
they're supposed to be doing, which is
basically focus on helping people
develop and and so in some ways I think
this this will require some pedagogical
changes. I mean, in one in one in one
regard, I've already spoken to this. I
think a lot of the actual teaching will
probably happen between the AI and the
individual. Namely, because the AI is
probably be more effective, you know, at
it. But that doesn't mean that the
classroom is no is no longer um useful.
I I think absolutely it still still will
be. It's just that the nature of the
classroom I think will probably change,
right? And so instead of that being a
place where information is basically
kind of downloaded to me and we all sit
there quietly and make notes in our in
our books, um it'll be a place where I
can I can then having now digested all
of these insights, right? And now having
effectively understood them more better
because I've worked with AI to make sure
and it's validated that I have
understood these concepts. I can now go
into a classroom environment and share
them right with others and we can
actually look at problems together and I
can hear other people's opinions and
insights and I can actually learn what
that how that process should be done
right how how do I respectfully ensure
my ideas are are made known and how do I
respectfully listen to others ideas how
do we how do we effectively work
together um constructively on problems
you know and so I think if if the
classroom starts to resemble that more I
ultimately think that that that will
help a lot with the socialization skills
which I think are becoming increasingly
more more difficult to instill
especially as people are most of young
people's lives are mediated through
devices and and and actually I think
practically that'll actually help
prepare them for the for the job market.
I mean because you know one things I I
you know whether someone has a degree or
not is matters to me less less and less
as as time goes on. What I care more
about is is the person a good and honest
person? Are they a hard worker? And and
when they're working as part of our
team, how effectively they do they work
with others and I so I think if the
classroom environment focus on honing
more of those skills that actually will
effectively prepare them better for for
for the job market.
>> Well, that's that that's very exciting
and also kind of, you know, wild to
think about, you know, students um Gene
and being able to really focus on those
those core values and those core skills.
Um, Matthew, as as you know, we prepare
to launch the Alexandria digitization
hub and we, you know, two scanners
coming in. We have a bunch more coming
in. Um, it seems as we're scanning more,
it does seem still that we're at the tip
of the iceberg. How much more work do we
have to do to to digitize the patrimony
of the church? I mean, how many how many
books are we talking about, you know,
hopefully in the next few years? Um, how
how does that look like um for our
audience who, you know, is wants to keep
up to date with that progress?
Well, I mean, you know, I think it's
it's I mean, hundreds of thousands and
millions of books. I mean, so the patron
of the church is is not small. So, in
that respect, it's daunting. It'll it'll
take um a lot of time, but but I I think
it's worth it. It's worth it. I mean, so
and again, we have to we have to like
it's important to, you know, to approach
this. I mean, there's there's kind of
critical doctrine and dogma, right?
there there's the works of the fathers
of the church, you know, uh, and and so
that's been our primary focus and and
we're we're getting deeper and deeper
into that. I I feel like by the end of
the of the summer, um, we'll probably
have the collective works of all the
fathers and doctors of the church made
available to anyone in the world in in
their own language for free, which is
which is pretty exciting. We already
have kind of a core magisterial teaching
is in there. And now we're going back to
the more ancient popes and trying to
digitize, you know, their their kind of
ancient writings and their ancient
encyclicals and things so that they
ensure to ensure that their voices are
added um to to the modern magisteria.
So, you know, I think in the next year
um we'll get a lot done. But one thing
that kind of excites me about this
project and you get this experience like
when you walk into one of these
libraries is is you know that a bunch of
those books haven't been open in 100
years, 200 years. And and if you were to
ask the librarian what's in that book, I
mean they could tell you what the title
is, right? But they don't even know,
right? So that to me is exciting because
I think there's probably a lot of
brilliant brilliant minds, brilliant
voices from the past who who have a lot
to say even to our contemporary world,
but because um nobody knows what they
what they have to say because those
books haven't been opened.
Unfortunately, their insights are just
kind of kind of lost to us. And so I I
what I what I'm excited about is this
process of digitizing these these books
and then of course making them available
through tools like Madison and Vulgate.
What's kind of really exciting to me
about it is that somebody may be asking
u you know a pretty typical theological
question and because we've now digitized
you know these these books these these
people's insights those insights can now
be brought to bear they may start
popping up in unusual places and so what
does it almost increases the surface
area for research which is exciting I
think for in academia but but it also
ensures that those insights may be
particularly useful to to to someone
right and so that could help them
hopefully constructively in their life
and it it may lead to to devotions you
know to to to to some of these scholars
and and we may have to reevaluate the
work and say actually that their
contributions are much more significant
than we thought and and maybe we should
spend more time thinking about it,
right? And so there could be more
spiritual devotions and more research
that happens as a result.
>> And and Father David, how do you see um
you know, bringing bringing to the the
modern era all these writers that have
you know have kind of been falling
asleep for the last couple centuries if
you know if these books haven't been
opened or if you know scholarship
focuses on a specific niche topic at
this moment. How do you think it's going
to inform the the dialogue within the
church and the dialogue with the wider
society having all these voices kind of
coming up to air now?
>> Well, I think you can only help because
there's uh uh to to make a an analogous
comment, a country that has only two or
three political parties only represents
the people that have those kinds of
opinions. But if you're in a country
with a 100 million people, you probably
need more opinions than two or three to
cover what what the people are about.
So, same thing here. There's there's uh
um a democratic
factor in this. The more people that
have more access to more resources,
uh letting people develop along their
the spirit of their own genius, their
own interests and all, it enhances
social conversation. uh it enhances the
possibilities for for broader justice,
broader uh human understanding whether
it's ecumenism among uh Christian
religions or other religions or even
just other ideological groups, other
nations uh other countries. It just
enhances those possibilities because it
doesn't limit the people. This is always
a criticism of a of a classroom is that
classroom has uh bright students uh not
so bright students and a bunch in the
middle. People are interested in
physical labor. If people are interested
in a well the classroom of one teacher
and 50 students can only rep represent
kind of one basic position. This kind of
structure allows for many kind of
genius's minds interest to be expressed
and developed. So it enhances social
conversation.
>> That's fantastic. Um, and I guess my
last question is how how do we think,
you know, for the for the wider church
um, as this as this technology, you
know, continues to to bring more and
more of these instruments um, to light
and and shares them around the world.
What are your what are your hopes for
for the church adopting this more, you
know, more widely, more broadly? There's
many many Pentipical universities around
the world. There's, you know,
universities around the world who might
not have access to this yet. Um, what
are your hopes and dreams as we look
towards the future?
>> Well, I mean,
the the last number of years has given
indication that it's foolish to make
long-term plans you know some beyond 3
months we just don't know what's going
to happen out there so I in one sense
it's uh it's running with this you know
there's a title of a book I think in the
1960s are you running with me Jesus you
know and it's with devotion with faith
with uh all goodwill to run forward with
this stuff to use this stuff as as best
we can but for me to predict It's we
wouldn't have predicted 3 years ago that
we would be where we are now with the
digitizing uh project. So to imagine in
the future, I'm not sure if that's the
best question to ask. It's a logical
question to ask, but how do we live
fully in the moment that uh that we're
in? You know, it's kind of that for me I
I have to agree. I I I think that what
we should be doing now is thinking about
um I think I think and I'm hoping that
with with this new pontificate this is
becoming more central focus is is
constituently what needs to be in place
in order to ensure that people flourish
and then and then then we kind of work
backwards and say how can this new
technology now and possibly in the
future help contribute to that
flourishing
and I think if we if we think of it more
like that given the power of this
technology and and the import Now that
it's it's going, you know, beyond these
these AI systems, disembodied AI systems
which live in, you know, large computing
clusters to now being embodied in robots
mean they're actually able to physically
interact in our world. We start thinking
about the import of that, it's going to
touch every facet of society, right? So
if we have a clear understanding of
where we we where human beings should be
headed, how this technology can help
enhance flourishing, that we can make
sure that we're we're basically focusing
our society's resources and developing
the technology in a way that will
optimize flourishing, right? as opposed
to uh impede it right by you know like
one of the things I I get concerned
about is um you know as a robots get
deployed more and more it's it's likely
to be the case people have more time on
their hands and and I I think I think
that's a good thing but for many people
could it could actually not be a good
thing it could end up impeding the
flourishing because they may choose to
use that time to do nothing but game
right or spend time in VR worlds or
spend more time in their devices or god
willing god forbid looking at porn or
something like that I mean so so I think
you know given that that's likely
to be the outcome for a lot of people. I
think it's it's really it's critical for
us um in the church to remember, you
know, it's, you know, flourishing, but
also the importance of evangelization,
right? We have to make sure that we're
we're the gospel. We're finding new ways
to deliver the gospel in ways that are
effective. We have to find ways to reach
those people who maybe who don't know
about the gospel and and and the
benefits of a Christian way of life, how
how enriching it is because maybe
they've never seen it or it's never been
explained to them. If we do that more
effectively, then people won't just kind
of like by default end up disappearing
into these virtual gaming worlds simply
because they don't know what they're
supposed to be doing with their lives,
right? Because they haven't had a chance
to discern what their gifts are and
figure out how to put those gifts to the
service of others and of God. And so I
this is why I think what like it's been
a real like honor privilege to work with
Father David because um you know being
someone who was working in technology
now, you know, for a good period of
time, I get very hopeful about the the
future of it. But one of the things I I
get concerned about is just how do how
do I effectively um uh deploy the
technology and and and and how do I how
do I even make a case for it? And so
when you meet people like Father David
who are very open-minded, right, who are
who who understand the problems and are
willing to willing to try try new things
out, right? It's exciting because
because because you know then they get a
chance to um to to show people to
demonstrate that that can work. And
ironically, maybe this is not entirely
maybe fair to say, but but I I have
found in Rome in particular, seeing is
believing, you know, um and at least
when it comes to like technology and
things. And I think so the more that we
can demonstrate um the benefits of the
technology, people can come, they can
see it for themselves, they can interact
with, they can touch with it, I think
the more likely it will it's likely to
scale and be adopted elsewhere. And
that's one of the reasons why I'm so
proud of what Father David's done at the
Pontific Orientals institute do because
it's it stands in Rome as probably one
of the most advanced universities
probably in Italy. Um and that was in
large part because Father David's just
looking at the problems and saying how
do we do this? And anyway, so it's I'm
very encouraged that that he's now in a
position that he can influence more
institutions now and I'm seeing a lot
more other other pontificities um get
excited and and be more willing to adopt
the technology.
>> I think we're going to be seeing great
things. Um, Matthew, Father David, thank
you so much for this very inspiring
conversation. Thank you, Ben. Thank you.